Hello, my friends, I'm looking of to the complete data structure and algorithms course in this video,
we are going to solve exercise number 80 and we are going to implement a circle queue in Java.
We have seen how the circular Q data structure work and the animation and in the video that we have
seen in the lectures and we implement circular Q and see the same as in Java, but with different syntax.
So please concentrate with me.
We are going to create a new Java class inside the series sources folder.
And by the way, you can get all this project source codes from the resources folder and they you do
me.
So I will create C Q Circle or Q and U Java class here called CQ.
Now let's create the same way that inside, because we need it to be performed as a as an array size
of circular Q.
This is the size of circular Q.
Now we need to create two could do 30 meters of front end of the year that we have seen in the lecture
that indicate which is different and which is the rear in order to get the wet when pushing and popping.
We need to or when we incubate a deck, we need to know where we need to insert.
Then, you know, or where is it to remove that last note?
OK.
So I will create an int items here.
It is for the valuable new insight, and it is of size, the size.
OK, you can define it like this, or if it is five, if you are defining it as five, OK, or you can
make it more general by making the constructor seek you here, you can make front at first equal to
minus one.
This is what we have agreed about it in there in the lecture, and despite using it here, we can specify
in size without specifying it.
And we can make end size when creating a new and size, then new items equal to this new items items
array equal to new item and a size that is passed by the perimeter.
OK.
OK, guys, it's very simple.
Now.
We can make it like this in that way, it's better now we have created a constructor that depends on
passing the size of the queue to create a new array called items, depending on the same size.
And we have int front and rear and we have the size of the circular queue.
No, let's start making the method here.
The methods
we start by the first one.
Public Boolean is full.
We start checking if the queue is full or not, if from equal equal to zero and rear equal equal to
size minus one
return and true.
OK.
This is checking for if there's the full, because if the front equal equal to zero and rear equal to
size minus one, then it is full because we need to check the two two pointers that are rear and the
front.
Or there is a new case if the front equal equal to the year plus one, because we said that the front
will be, it will indicate the element that it is when you call a pop or deck, it will select the element
that the front is indicating why that is when we need to include a new element within when we need to
insert a new element that will indicate the position where it is next to it will be inserting than you
note.
For that, we need to return.
And true because in this case, if front equal, equal to rear plus one, it is full Q.
Otherwise, if there is no condition like this, return false.
OK.
Now, let's see if it is empty the same way in the same concept, we are going to check if it is empty
by using the front because it's it's easier.
So Boolean public Boolean is empty.
If front equal equal to minus one.
Then return true.
Otherwise else return false.
OK.
This is how we check if the queue is empty by checking the front.
If it is equal minus one.
OK.
It's very simple because we initialized the front by minus one.
Now, let's add the elements.
This is in you or it is a more complex method than there is full or is empty.
So we start by making.
Thank you.
It took in the perimeter to the elements that we are going to insert it into the side of the queue and
we check if is full.
We cannot add anything.
So system thought out dot, print and queue is full.
OK.
If the queue is full, we cannot add anything else
else, what to do.
I need to open brackets if front equal, equal minus one, then return
front equal to zero.
And make their years be equal to a year plus one module size.
You remember this algorithm, guys.
It's very important because if you are making real +1 modules size and we make it, then you mean value
of 30.
This is the trick behind the Inca, and we will see it in the deck.
OK.
Because in cue and deck inside a circular queue is depending almost 99 percent on this modulo size.
So this is very important and we have seen it in C in the same concept.
OK.
30 year element.
And then we display a method, a message called the inserted
inserted plus element.
OK.
This is how we insert elements inside.
You know, let's remove an element from that.
Cue the same concept.
And we have seen in the previous video public int it returns int deck.
And it will not take any perimeter because we are just decking, we are just removing an element that
it is and the first or the oldest element that have been inserted into a circular queue.
So end element if it is empty.
We are not going to remove anything because there is nothing.
Okay.
So system that out, that print and end queue
is empty
returned minus one.
OK.
This is why we returned minus one because it is empty.
Otherwise, it would be start removing the element and now assigning the elements at index of.
So this and this affront will indicate the element at which we are getting that correct element.
So for that, we have used the front and for this, we have used that rear.
You see guys, when in queuing, insert certain you'd need.
That is when decking, where removing you need therefrom.
This is the algorithm.
This is the importance of the usage of the front and the rear
valuables game.
So front equal to rear, a front, equal to rear.
Then what happens?
We are going to create frankly minus one again every year, equal to minus one.
We are resetting their elements, their front and real rear if Q has only one element.
Otherwise, we use front.
We move front to the front plus +1 modulo size gain.
This is the trick behind using the model.
And that in queuing in deck inside air is like a circular Q or circular to a return that.
Now, let's test our program.
But before I need to make a new method, it called display that print the display, the status of the
circular Q so void display
function to display the status of the Q and I tell if or what can be created in the blue.
So if it is empty, then we print them that out.
Dot print and an empty Q OK.
Otherwise, if it is not empty, we are going to print system that out dot, print and end the front.
Is.
Plus, front
and sister out the sprint and the rear.
Real would be rear, OK?
And.
Let's see the elements inside them.
So system that out, that brand alarm items and items.
Bioprinting by using the falou four and I equal to feront eye does not equal to the eye, equal to eye
plus one because we are moving at modulo size.
OK.
This is the algorithm behind moving the cursor through the elements of
circular Q so brain.
Items.
At Index I plus the space gay.
And system that the brand, Ellen's items.
OK, now let's see what happens here.
If we call it in the main method of public, let's create the driver class public static void, main
string parts, we will create secure que equal to new secure and we pass the size of five.
Now let's start if we start thinking, removing the element that will display for us minus one because
there is no element so cute.
Thank you, Juan.
OK.
Let me copy this.
Right to.
Three, four and five.
Okay, if we call HQ six, it for return falls at beholds phase two in cubicles front equal equal to
zero and rear equal to size minus one.
And that's cue dot display.
Or we can display cue the display.
Let's run and see.
OK, let's run this.
That's it on this.
Oops!
Models size size is equal to zero.
Yes, because we didn't realize it here.
OK.
Size equal to see you.
We need to go to that constructor and put this size equal to size because we didn't initialize it and
dig the perimeter that we have passed.
Let's run, Nancy.
And here we go, inserting one two three four five.
The front is zero items one two three four five four and that is equal to four.
And here we go.
We have correctly make everything works in the C Q and the circular Q.
OK, so you can get all of these data structures from the resources folder and you.